"The Third Way to Boost NAD+"
There are three
NAD+ boosting strategies:
Increasing the supply
of NAD+ precursors
is just one way.
The other two
are having the body make more,
by activating
NAD+-synthesizing enzymes,
or have the body use less,
by, for example,
conserving it, by using less.
Besides sirtuins,
the major consumers
of NAD+ are PARP-1 and CD38.
PARP-1 is an enzyme
that uses NAD+ to repair DNA.
The more oxidative DNA damage,
the more single
and double stranded DNA breaks,
the more enzymes like PARP-1
need to be activated
to come to the rescue.
This uses up a lot of NAD.
As DNA damage
accumulates with age,
the rising need
for repair enzymes like PARP-1
causes a major drain
on NAD+ levels.
Exposing cells in vitro
to DNA damaging agents,
such as gamma radiation
or genotoxic chemicals,
can cause an 80
to 90 percent drop
in NAD+ levels
within a matter of minutes.
This has led to the search
for PARP-1 blockers
to preserve NAD+ levels,
but rather than blocking
DNA repair,
why not work to prevent
so much damage
in the first place?
For example,
the severe oxidative stress
of a high-fat diet
can lead to PARP-1 activation
and NAD+ depletion in mice,
but NAD+ levels can be
"dramatically restored"
by feeding them
"purple sweet potato color,"
the natural
anthocyanin pigments
found in purple sweet potatoes.
Or, of course, you can just not
feed them a high-fat diet.
DNA repair is a good thing.
PARP-1 may be
one of the reasons
NAD+-boosting interventions
can improve healthspans
and lifespans
in laboratory animals.
Greater PARP activity
strongly correlates
with longer lifespan
across about a dozen
mammalian species,
and the PARP activity
of human centenarians
averages 60 percent higher
than younger controls.
However, persistent activation
can lead to NAD+ depletion,
and overactivation
can lead to cell death.
So, we should try to keep
oxidative stress to a minimum.
CD38 is another major guzzler
of NAD+.
It's an enzyme that uses NAD+
found concentrated
on the surfaces
of immune cells
and robustly induced
in the context of inflammation.
The rise of CD38 activity
with age
has been blamed on persistent
"inflammaging" activation,
the rise in systemic low-grade
inflammation in our bodies
when we get older,
which may be a major culprit
for falling NAD+ levels.
For example, blocking CD38
has been found
to raise NAD+ levels
in old mice
comparable to that
of younger mice.
So, oxidation and inflammation
can lead to a drop
in NAD+ levels,
due to the excess activation
of the NAD+ consuming enzymes.
This may explain why
protective sirtuin activity
is reduced in obesity,
a condition characterized
by oxidative stress
and inflammation.
A study of identical twin pairs
in which one, on average,
was obese and the other not,
found significantly
less sirtuin expression
in the obese twin,
despite having
the same genetics.
And randomize people
to a six-month trial
of 25 percent
calorie restriction,
and you can show a boost
in sirtuin expression
along with a decrease
in DNA damage.
Protein restriction
may have a similar effect,
since men and women
with higher protein intake
tend to have lower levels
of NAD+ in their blood,
thought to be due
to the oxidative stress
induced by protein
breakdown byproducts.
If oxidation and inflammation
are responsible
for a drop in NAD+ levels,
then what about the antioxidant
and anti-inflammatory
phytonutrients
in healthy plant foods?
After screening
more than 14,000 compounds,
almost all flavonoids
were found to be effective
in a test for CD38 inhibition.
The two most effective
were cyanidin,
found in red cabbage
and blackberries,
and quercetagetin,
found in marigold flower tea.
Another study found
the three most potent compounds
were luteolin, kuromanin,
and luteolinidin.
Luteolin is found concentrated
in oregano, radicchio,
and chrysanthemum tea.
Kuromanin is found
in black berries, purple corn,
and hibiscus tea.
Corn tortillas are
surprisingly easy to make;
so why not choose blue
or purple masa
to make them even healthier?
Luteolinidin,
found to increase NAD+
in the hearts of rats,
can be found in red sorghum,
one of the components
of my prebiotic BROL mix,
when I can find it.
The flavonoid apigenin
is a well-established
CD38 inhibitor.
When given to mice,
apigenin boosts NAD+ levels
by about 50 percent,
which is what people would get
taking the maximum
tolerable daily dose of NR.
The best sources are parsley
and chamomile tea.
A wide range of flavonoids
found in green tea, turmeric,
and fruits and vegetables
have also been found
to prevent NAD+ depletion
in human cells in vitro
at levels found in the blood
after consumption.
How much do you have to eat,
though?
Proanthocyanidins have been
found to lower PARP-1
and CD38 expression in rats.
NAD+ and sirtuin activity
was significantly boosted
at the human equivalent dose
of about 280 milligrams a day.
How much is that?
That's the amount
of proanthocyanidins
found in a single apple.
You could also reach that dose
eating two plums,
a half cup of wild blueberries,
a little over a teaspoon
of cinnamon,
or a little over a tablespoon,
like four teaspoons,
of cocoa powder.
Quercetin is another suppressor
of PARP-1 and CD38
shown to increase
sirtuin activity in mice.
The concentration necessary
to lower PARP-1 in vitro
can be achieved by taking
a quercetin supplement,
but typical supplement
manufacturers'
recommended doses
are up to 100 times
the average daily
dietary intake.
Thankfully, food works too.
Researchers fried up
one and a half yellow onions
and raised
quercetin blood levels
to about 75 percent there.
And so, two onions might do it.
There's no long-term
safety data
on high-dose
flavonoid supplementation;
so, public health researchers
suggest
"caution should be exercised
in ingesting them
at levels above which
would be obtained
from a typical
vegetarian diet."